Guide to the Holocaust Survivors Film Project Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Holocaust Survivors Film Project records
1978-1986
MS 1909
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(2 boxes)
The Holocaust Survivors Film Project (HSFP) was a grass roots project to videotape testimony of survivors. The records document the establishment of the project and its growth from a volunteer effort to an established academic research collection, now known as the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies, at the Yale University Library. The collection includes administrative and financial records, such as correspondence, press releases, meeting minutes, grant proposals, pamphlets, and clippings.
Holocaust Survivors Film Project
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Other records related to the Holocaust Survivors Film Project and its successor organization, the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies, are maintained by the Yale University Archives in Manuscripts and Archives.
Biographical / Historical
In 1979, a television specialist, Laurel Vlock, and a survivor of the Holocaust, psychiatrist Dr. Dori Laub, launched a project to document the personal memories of Holocaust witnesses using the medium of video. They helped form a grass roots organization, the Holocaust Survivors Film Project (HSFP), together with local survivors, under the leadership of William Rosenberg, academic consultants led by Yale Professor Geoffrey Hartman, and other community members committed to this urgent task. Initially, this group videotaped almost 200 testimonies; produced, with New York's WNEW-TV, Forever Yesterday, an Emmy award-winning documentary; and created About the Holocaust, a specially prepared documentary for secondary schools. In 1981 Yale University accepted all the original testimony tapes as a formal deposit. The following year, with the aid of a start-up grant from the Charles H. Revson Foundation, the Video Archive was established as part of the University's Sterling Memorial Library. Additional information about the HSFP and its successor organization, the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies, can be found at the Video Archive's web site: http://www.library.yale.edu/testimonies.
Scope and Contents
The Holocaust Survivors Film Project (HSFP) was a grass roots project to videotape testimony of survivors. The records document the establishment of the project and its growth from a volunteer effort to an established academic research collection, now known as the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies, at the Yale University Library. The collection includes administrative and financial records, such as correspondence, press releases, meeting minutes, grant proposals, pamphlets, and clippings.
Of particular interest is the correspondence between members of the HSFP (particularly Dori Laub, Laurel Vlock, Geoffrey Hartman, Malcolm Webber, Melvin Ditman, and Ludwig Friedenberg) and survivors; grant funding agencies; various affiliate projects and Jewish organizations, such as Yad Vashem; television stations; scholars of the Holocaust, including Elie Wiesel, Yizhak Arad, and Yehuda Bauer; representatives from the President's Comission on the Holocaust; and potential repositories to house the HSFP tapes.
Arrangement
The records follow two arrangements that reflect how they were received. Administrative and financial records are followed by records in an alphabetical filing system. This latter group of records includes generic files and subject files.
Holocaust survivors -- Interviews; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945) -- Personal narratives; Video recording; Holocaust Survivors Film Project
- Administrative records, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
- Financial records, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
  Scope and Contents
  The financial records include correspondence, particularly with then treasurer Ludwig Friedenberg, related to donations and expenditures for HSFP tapings, including pages from an accounting book for the documentary about the New Haven Farband.
- Alphabetic files
  - A, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Correspondence and agreement between the HSFP and Laurel Vlock and Dori Laub.
  - About the Holocaust study guide, Circa 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - B, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Boston, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Documents related to establishment and management of an affiliate taping project in Boston, Massachusetts.
  - Budget, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - By-laws, Circa 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - C, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16-16A)
  - D, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Development of the HSFP, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Publicity packet, including short history of the project.
  - F, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Foundations, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Lists of foundations to which the HSFP applied, or considered applying, for funding.
  - Future interviewees, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Information regarding potential interviewees.
  - G, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Correspondence with Yale President A. Bartlett Giamatti, Itzhak Gottesman, and others.
  - Grant proposals, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - H, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hartford, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Documents related to establishment and management of an affiliate taping project in Hartford, Connecticut, including the production of film The Survivors Among Us, which was screened on public television.
  - Holocaust Survivors Film Project, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    Agendas, press conferences, organizational charts, newsletters, grant proposals, and a transcript of a presentation given at press conference at the home of William Rosenberg.
  - Initial prospectus, Circa 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Interviewer psychology, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Documents related to interviewer methodology and training.
  - J, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jerusalem Concentration Camp Conference, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Correspondence (some in Hebrew), photographs and documents regarding Dori Laub's participation in the Fourth International Historical Conference in Jerusalem.
  - K, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Katherine Engel Center, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Correspondence related to taping efforts at Katherine Engel Center in New York City, staff lists, taping schedules, and taping procedures.
  - Kline, Dana, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Transcript of interview conducted by and correspondence with Dana Kline.
  - L, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Laub, Dori, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Packet of photocopied correspondence, brochures, and other materials documenting Dori Laub's involvement in the HSFP.
  - M, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Meeting minutes, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - N, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Correspondence and photocopy of New Haven Foundation grant proposal submitted in 1979.
  - National Endowment for the Arts and National Endowment for the Humanities, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Correspondence, clippings, and other materials related to the submission of an NEH grant.
  - Newsletter, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Norfolk, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Documents related to possibility of establishing an affiliate taping project in Norfolk, Virginia.
  - Oral history projects, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Correspondence with Yehuda Bauer, among others, and photocopies of manuscripts on oral history and the Holocaust.
  - P, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Palm Beach, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Documents related to establishment and management of an affiliate taping project in Palm Beach, Florida.
  - Position paper regarding the relevance of the HSFP for New Haven, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Publicity, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Clippings, photocopies of letters from important community figures, press releases and other materials used to promote the mission of the HSFP.
  - R, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Various correspondence and photocopy of Revson grant proposal.
  - Research proposal, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Paper by Dori Laub suggesting study of survivor adaptation to trauma.
  - Résumés, Circa 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Résumés from interviewer candidates.
  - S, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - St.Louis (German ocean liner), 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 28-28A)
    Photocopies of manuscript materials and photographs, clippings, and correpsondence related to two film projects: Flight from Destiny, a documentary about the journey of the ocean liner St.Louis, and a film about the Jewish community of Danzig. Includes a series of articles in German from the periodical Stern about the St. Louis.
  - T, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Tape inventory, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    A list of the first wave of testimonies recorded starting in 1979 with short biographical sketches.
  - Television programs, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Correspondence with television stations regarding screenings to documentaries made with HSFP materials.
  - Transcripts of Laurel Vlock's tapes, Circa 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Transcriptions of Laurel Vlock describing HSFP.
  - U, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - V, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Memos, budgets, and job descriptions.
  - Video Archive, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Materials related to the establishment of a Video Archive for HSFP testimonies at Yale.
  - Video Archive requests, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Requests from various organizations interested in forming an affiliate with the HSFP/Video Archive.
  - Video Archive staffing, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Videotaping, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Letter from Geoffrey Hartman regarding provision of mental health support to survivors after taping sessions.
  - W, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Weiss, Lillian, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Correspondence between Lillian Weiss and Dori Laub.
  - Y, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)